Guide to the United Women Firefighters Records WAG.057
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Women Firefighters Records
1957-2022
1979-1993
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Women Firefighters
Berkman, Brenda
WAG.057
15.25 Linear Feet in 13 record cartons, 5 manuscript boxes, 6 oversize folders, 2 folders in shared housing, and 3 flat files.
47 videocassettes
19 videodiscs (dvd)
38.95 Gigabytes
2 videocassettes (vhs)
The United Women Firefighters (UWF) was founded in 1982 as a support organization for women firefighters in the New York City Fire Department. The UWF was founded to deal with the occupational and sexual discrimination women firefighters faced. The collection, dating from 1957 to 2022, covers founder Brenda Berkman's career, legal cases (Brenda Berkman et al. v. City of New York et al.; Brenda Berkman et al. v. City of New York et al., Appeal; and Brenda Berkman v. City of New York, Carlos Rivera, and Selig Ginsberg), and the founding and development of the United Women Firefighters of New York City and the related national support group, Women in Fire Service (WFS, alternately known as Women in Fire Suppression). The collection contains scrapbook material, personal correspondence, legal documents, organizational files, subject files, clippings, photographs, videos, and memorabilia. Also featured are audio visual and born-digital materials of presentations, news segments, interviews, photographs, and speeches by Brenda Berkman on behalf of the United Women Firefighters.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The original donation of material to the Wagner Labor Archives was made by Brenda Berkman and the United Women Firefighters in 1987. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1987.005 and 1987.007. Berkman donated an additional four boxes in 2002. She made subsequent donations in 2005 and 2011. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are NPA.2005.179, 2011.111, and 2012.064. One box of photographs and memorabilia found in repository in 2013 was added to the collection in 2017. The accession number associated with these materials is 2017.021. Brenda Berkman sent an additional box of materials related to her continued advocacy for women firefighters in 2016. The accession number associated with this gift is 2017.037. Brenda Berkman donated eight posters from events celebrating women firefighters in December 2017. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.003. Brenda Berkman made a subsequent donation in April 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.137. Joanne Jacobs donated an accretion of three folders of documents and photographs in January 2019; the accession number associated with this gift is 2019.061. Brenda Berkman donated an accretion of two folders in March 2023; the accession number associated with this gift is 2023.053.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in four series, two of which have been further divided into subseries. Series II: Legal Files is divided into subseries by legal case. Legal files in each subseries are arranged chronologically, and subject files are arranged alphabetically by subject. Series III: Organizational Files is divided into two subseries by organization. Files within remaining series files are arranged alphabetically by subject or record type. The series and subseries arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I: Brenda Berkman Papers, 1977-2005
Series II: Legal Files, 1979-1993 Subseries A: Brenda Berkman et al. v. City of New York et al. (Case No. 79, C 1813)--Class Action Suit Legal Documents, 1979-1986; Subseries B: Brenda Berkman et al. v. City of New York et al. (Case No. 79, C 1813)--Class Action Suit Subject Files, 1979-1990; Subseries C: Brenda Berkman et al. v. City of New York et al. (Case no. 82-7654)--Appeal, 1982; Subseries D: Brenda Berkman v. New York City Fire Department, Carlos Rivera, and Selig Ginsberg, (Case no. E-92-0575), 1987-1993
Series III: Organizational Files, 1977-2002 Subseries A: United Women Firefighters, 1977-2002; Subseries B: Women in Fire Suppression and Women in the Fire Service, 1983-1999
Series IV: Photographs and Memorabilia, circa 1980-1999
Historical Note
The United Women Firefighters (UWF) was founded in 1982 by the first group of New York City women firefighters to address occupational and sexual discrimination in the New York City Fire Department (NYCFD, also known as the FDNY by the department). Modeled on groups like the Vulcan Society (representing African-American firefighters), the UWF assists women firefighters who have encountered a wide range of problems on the job, from ill-fitting equipment to unjust probation and sexual assault. They have lobbied for training for all officers and firefighters on issues related to women on the job. Representatives of the organization have developed ties with other women firefighters' organizations, including the national coalition, Women in Fire Service. The United Women Firefighters publishes a monthly newsletter, the Voice Alarm.
The FDNY began accepting applications from women for the position of firefighter in 1977, but did not hire any women until after Brenda Berkman successfully sued the City of New York on behalf of herself and other women who had passed the written examination. Berkman, a law student at New York University at the time of her application, sued the City under the 1964 Civil Rights Act, questioning the validity of the physical exam. In 1982, Judge Charles Sifton ruled that the City had indeed discriminated against women through its physical exam, known as the 3040 exam, which included tests that were biased against women and unrelated to a firefighter's future performance on the job. The suit and Sifton's ruling sparked controversy in the Fire Department and the media. Litigation related to this original ruling continued until 1988. Berkman, who was a founding member and president of the United Women Firefighters, filed an additional lawsuit against the FDNY in 1992 challenging incidents of sexual harassment directed at women in the department.
Related Materials
Other materials relating to Brenda Berkman and women firefighters in New York City are found in the Brenda Berkman Papers on September 11, 2011 (WAG 299).
Scope and Contents
The United Women Firefighters Records (dates 1957-2022, bulk 1979-1993) document the career of firefighter Brenda Berkman and the founding and operation of the United Women Firefighters. The collection consists of scrapbooks, personal correspondence, legal documents, organizational files, subject files, clippings, memorabilia, photographs, and videos. A large portion of the collection documents the life and career of founder Brenda Berkman, the successful legal actions Berkman brought against the City of New York and the New York City Fire Department (Berkman v. the City of New York; Berkman v. NYCFD) between 1977 and 1993, and the unsuccessful appeal by the City of New York to Judge Charles Sifton's 1982 ruling that the City had discriminated against women through its physical exam. Materials related more directly to Berkman's career include scrapbooks of her personal achievements; clippings, videos, and ephemera documenting her advocacy for women in male-dominated professions; recruitment correspondence; and condolences sent to Berkman following the September 11, 2001 World Trade Center attacks. Also featured are audio visual and born-digital materials of presentations, news segments, interviews, photographs, and speeches by Brenda Berkman on behalf of the United Women Firefighters. The collection also documents the founding and operation of the United Women Firefighters, and the related national support group, Women in Fire Service. These organizational files largely consist of newspapers clippings, correspondence, and FDNY recruitment and sexual-harassment training documents.
Legal documents.; Correspondence.; Minutes (administrative records); New York (N.Y.).; Fire fighters -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Sex discrimination in employment -- New York (State) -- New York.; Sex discrimination against women -- New York (State) -- New York.; Women in the civil service -- New York (State) -- New York.; Women fire fighters -- New York (State) -- New York.; Women's rights -- New York (State) -- New York.; Women -- New York (State) -- New York -- Societies, etc.; Clippings (information artifacts); Manuscripts; Videocassettes.; Slides (photographs); Photographs.; Interviews.; Speeches.; Women in the Fire Service (Organization); Women in Fire Suppression (Organization); New York (N.Y.). Fire Department; Berkman, Brenda; United Women Firefighters
- Series I: Brenda Berkman Papers, 1957-2016; 3.5 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, and 2 oversize folders; 22 videocassettes; 13 videodiscs (dvd)
  Scope and Content Note
  This series dates from 1957 to 2016 and includes biographical material about Brenda Berkman, clippings related to her career, correspondence from her legal practice, and scrapbooks, primarily dealing with the case Berkman v. City of New York. The series also contains materials related to Berkman's advocacy on behalf of women firefighters, including recruitment correspondence, training documents for the Candidate Physical Ability Test (CPAT), handbooks, manuals, and ephemera from conferences and public events about women in male-dominated professions. Additionally, there are awards, videos, interviews, and clippings documenting Berkman's career achievements as well as correspondence and letters of support following the September 11, 2001 World Trade Center attacks.
  Materials added to this series in 2017 include additional ephemera, photos, flyers, and organizing materials related to Berkman's advocacy for women firefighters and 9/11 first responders. They include flyers, programs, transcripts, and memorabilia from several of Berkman's These materials largely date from 2011 to 2016 and include photographs from a panel event at Tamiment Library honoring women first responders on the 15th anniversary of 9/11.
  Biographical / Historical
  Brenda Berkman was born in 1951, and became interested in firefighting as a young girl. She earned her B.A. from St. Olaf College in Minnesota, an M.A. in History at Indiana University, a J.D. from New York University Law School, and an M.S. in Fire Protection Management from the City University of New York. At the time of her application to the New York Fire Department, she was a law student at New York University. Berkman is a founding member and former president of the United Women Firefighters from 1982 to 1986 and served as trustee of the Women in Fire Service from 1983 to 1992. She taught at the FDNY fire academy and the United States National Fire Academy. Berkman was a featured participant in the PBS program, Sex, Power, and the Workplace (1992) and was the subject of the Off-Broadway play, Firework (2002). Her story and that of her fellow women firefighters is the focus of the documentary, Taking the Heat: The First Women Firefighters of New York City (2006). She was promoted to Captain in 2002, only the third woman to achieve that rank.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject and format.
  - Award Nominations and Applications, 1984-2001 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Awards and Recognition, 1994-2008 (Box 10, Folder 2-3, Box Shared Tamiment MSOS007, Folder 1)
  - Banner -- "Welcome Brenda Berkman", undated (Flat-file-folder 4, Tray 3)
  - Biographical, 1984-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Candidate Physical Ability Test (CPAT), 1999-2001 (Box 10, Folder 7-10)
  - CD -- Women 2.0 Media Project, 2010 (Box 13)
  - Clippings, 1979-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 2001-2008 (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS007, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 2014-2016 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence -- Children, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence -- Legal Practice, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence -- Recruitment, 1999-2003 (Box 10, Folder 12-14)
  - DVD -- Emma on the Loose Featuring an Interview with Brenda Berkman, Show 22, 2001; cuid57 (Box 13)
  - DVD -- Women in the Fire Service: Captain Brenda Berkman, Presented at Oklahoma State University, 2004 March 5; cuid58 (Box 13)
  - Eulogy for Firefighter Lorraine Cziko, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Firehouse Closing, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 13-14, Box Shared Tamiment C001, Folder 1)
  - Magazine Articles on Women Firefighters, 2011-2014 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Many Faces, One Purpose: A Manager's Handbook on Women in Firefighting, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Portraits in Courage Exhibit, 1993-1995 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Post 9-11, 2001-2002 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
  - Post 9-11 -- Children's Artwork, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 5-7)
  - Programs and Newspaper Clippings -- Brenda Berkman Youth, 1957-1973 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Programs and Newspaper Clippings -- Brenda Berkman and Women on 9-11, 2001-2011 (Box 11, Folder 9-11, Box Shared Tamiment C001, Folder 1)
  - Recommendations for Improving the Recruitment and Hiring of Los Angeles Firefighters, 2015 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Recruitment, 2000-2003 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbooks, 1977-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5-13)
  - Scrapbook -- Promotion to Lieutenant, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 13-15)
  - Speaking Events and Press, 2005-2006 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - "Terror Dream," by Susan Faludi (photocopy), 2007 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - "Thirty-Six Views of One World Trade" Exhibit - Programs and Flyers, 2014-2015 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Video -- 9/11 Firefighter Footage; Entering WTC North Tower; and Revised Women of Ground Zero, undated; cuid59 (Box 14)
  - Video -- 9/11 Special, Lifetime, 2001; cuid60 (Box 12)
  - Video -- Berkman, Brenda Early Press "Job 2215 R/I", undated; cuid61 (Box 14)
  - Video -- Berkman, Brenda Excerpts of Interview with Bann Roy, undated; cuid62 (Box 13)
  - Video -- Berkman, Brenda featured on Firefighter History, undated; cuid63 (Box 14)
  - Video -- Berkman, Brenda Interview on the ATN Channel 7 "11am" Program, Sydney, Australia, 1999 May 18; cuid64 (Box 12)
  - Video -- Berkman, Brenda Interview, Fire Department New York City: First Female Firefighter in USA, 1999 May 14; cuid65 (Box 12)
  - Video -- Berkman, Brenda Interview with Noelle Walker Stories About 9/11, 2001; cuid66 (Box 14)
  - Video -- Berkman, Brenda Interview on WCCO TV, undated; cuid67 (Box 12)
  - Video -- Berkman, Brenda of Ladder Company 11, NYC featured on Channel 8 Local News, 2002 March 8; cuid68 (Box 14)
  - Video -- Berkman, Brenda on the Charlie Rose Show, 1997 August 1; cuid69 (Box 12)
  - Video -- Berkman, Brenda on NBC Nightly News, the Rosie O'Donnell Show, and Pure Oxygen/Everyday Matters, 2001; cuid70 (Box 13)
  - Video -- Berkman, Brenda Press Conference, 1992 April 23-25; cuid71 (Box 14)
  - Video -- Berkman, Brenda Segment from NOW Legal Defense & Education Fund, undated; cuid72 (Box 14)
  - Video -- Female 9/11 First Responders on Good Morning America and Entertainment Tonight Excerpts, 2007 October 29; cuid73 (Box 14)
  - Video -- Female 9/11 First Responders clips from Good Morning America, Entertainment Tonight, NBC Nightly News, and CNN, 2001 October 29 - 2002 March 5; cuid74 (Box 13)
  - Video -- MessTV Episode 81, 2001 October 20; cuid75 (Box 12)
  - Video -- Promotion Day, 1994 September 29; cuid76 (Box 14)
  - Video -- St. Olaf Commencement, 2002 May 26; cuid77 (Box 14)
  - Video -- "Women Heroes on 9/11/01" NBC Nightly News and WNBC Television Segments, 2001 December, 2001 December 1; cuid78 (Box 14)
  - Video -- Women at Ground Zero with Senator Hillary Clinton, 2002 November 8; cuid79 (Box 13)
  - Video -- The Women of Ground Zero, 2002 February 6; cuid80 (Box 13)
  - Video -- Women's History Month, 2004 March; cuid81 (Box 13)
  - White House Fellowship Program, 1997; cuid82 (Box 10, Folder 4-6)
  - Women in Firefighting: Walking the Legal Tightrope, 2001 October 11-12 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Women in Fire Service -- Correspondence and Clippings, 1984-1995, 2001-2007 (Box 11, Folder 17-18)
  - Women in Fire Service -- Handbooks and Pamphlets, 1991-1999 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - United Women Firefighters Advocacy Work, 2016 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Women 2.0 Media Project, 2010 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Women 9/11 First Respoders Panel Discussion at Tamiment Library -- Event Photographs, 2016 September 13 (Box 16, Folder 10)
- Series II: Legal Files, 1979-1993; 4 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons
  The series consists of legal documents and subject files from court cases brought by Brenda Berkman against the City of New York and the New York City Fire Department between 1977 and 1993, and from an unsuccessful appeal by the City of New York to Judge Charles Sifton's 1982 ruling that the City had discriminated against women through its physical exam. The series includes materials from the following cases: Brenda Berkman et al. v. City of New York et al. (Case No. 79, C 1813) Class Action Suit (also known as "Berkman v. City of New York"), 1977-1990; Brenda Berkman et al. v. City of New York et al. (Case no. 82-7654) Appeal, 1982 (also known as "Berkman v. City of New York, Appeal"); and Brenda Berkman v. New York City Fire Department, Carlos Rivera, and Selig Ginsberg (Case no. E-92-0575), 1991-1993 (also known as "Berkman v. NYCFD").
  This series is divided into three subseries by legal case. Subseries A: Brenda Berkman et al. v. City of New York et al. (Case No. 79, C 1813)--Class Action Suit Legal Documents and Subseries B: Brenda Berkman et al. v. City of New York et al. (Case No. 79, C 1813)--Class Action Suit Subject Files address the same lawsuit but have been divided based on official legal records and personal records.
  - Subseries A: Brenda Berkman et al. v. City of New York et al. (Case No. 79, C 1813) -- Class Action Suit, Legal Documents, 1979-1986
    This subseries is arranged chronologically by the filing date of plaintiff and defendant papers or date of testimony.
    This subseries is comprised of legal documents (defendants' filings, exhibits, plaintiff's filings, and testimony), relating to the court case Berkman v. City of New York. This material covers not only the original case, but seven subsequent suits related to the dismissal and reinstatement with back-pay of firefighters Brenda Berkman and Zaida Gonzalez in 1983, the harassment cases of firefighters Katrina Cannon and Ella McNair, and the revised physical exam, 1162.
    - Complaint -- Class Action Suit (decided Mar 4, 1982), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Depositions -- Berkman (decided Mar 4, 1982), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Plaintiff's Papers (decided Mar 4, 1982) I-II, 1980 - 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16-19)
    - Memorandum, Decision, and Order (decided Mar 4, 1982) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Defendant's Papers (decided Dec 8, 1983) I-IV (Box 1, Folder 21-24)
    - Memorandum and Order (decided Dec 8, 1983) (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Plaintiff's Papers (decided Dec 8, 1983) (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Plaintiff's Papers (decided Dec 8, 1983) I-IX (Box 2, Folder 1-9)
    - Testimony (decided Dec 8, 1983) I-VII (Box 2, Folder 10-16)
    - Plaintiff's Papers (decided May 13, 1986) I, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Plaintiff's Papers (decided May 13, 1986), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Plaintiff's Papers (decided Nov 6, 1986), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Plaintiff's Papers (decided Oct 24, 1986) I-II, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
    - Plaintiff's Papers (decided Oct 8, 1985) I-III (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
    - Plaintiff's Papers (decided May 13, 1986) I-II, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
    - Testimony (decided Oct 8, 1985) I-V (Box 3, Folder 10-14)
    - Plaintiff's Papers (decided Feb 17, 1987), 1985 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Plaintiff's Papers (decided May 13, 1986) (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Defendant's Papers (decided Feb 17, 1987) I-II, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
    - Defendant's Papers (decided Feb 17, 1987), 1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Order (decided Feb 17, 1987), 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Plaintiff's Papers (decided Feb 17, 1987) I-III, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
    - Class Action Suit -- Proceedings, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Subseries B: Brenda Berkman et al. v. City of New York et al. (Case No. 79, C 1813) -- Class Action Suit, Subject Files, 1979-1990
    This subseries is comprised of subject files (clippings, correspondence, notes and research) relating to the court case Berkman v. City of New York. This material covers not only the original case, but seven subsequent suits related to the dismissal and reinstatement with back-pay of firefighters Brenda Berkman and Zaida Gonzalez in 1983, the harassment cases of firefighters Katrina Cannon and Ella McNair, and the revised physical exam, 1162.
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by subject or document type.
    - Cannon, Katrina (I-III), 1986 (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
    - Correspondence, 1982-1990 (Box 4, Folder 9-16)
    - McNair, Ella, 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Notes and Research, 1979-1987 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Subseries C: Brenda Berkman et al. v. City of New York et al. (Case no. 82-7654) -- Appeal, 1982
    This subseries consists of legal documents related to the unsuccessful appeal by the City of New York to Judge Sifton's 1982 ruling in Berkman v. City of New York.
    - Appeal, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Appeal -- Exhibits -- Transcriptions of Tapes, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Subseries D: Brenda Berkman v. New York City Fire Department, Carlos Rivera, and Selig Ginsberg (Case no. E-92-0575), 1987-1993
    This subseries consists of subject files, and includes correspondence, clippings, court papers, medical records, and press conference materials concerning Berkman's 1992 sexual harassment suit (Berkman v. NYCFD) against the New York City Fire Department, Fire Commissioner Carlos Rivera, and departmental physician, Dr. Selig Ginsberg.
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by subject and record type.
    - Chronology, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Clippings, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 23-28)
    - Demonstration -- Women's Action Coalition at City Hall, 1992 September 10 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - FDNY Policies, 1987-1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Legal Papers, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Medical, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Notes and Research, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Press Conference -- City Council, City Hall, 1992 April 23 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Press Conference -- City Council, City Hall, 1992 July 19 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Press Conference -- National Organization of Women (NOW), 1992 May 29 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Press Releases, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Subseries E. General Legal Files
    - Equal Employment Opportunity Claim, 1993-2003 (Box Shared Tamiment 165, Folder 9)